Now that our server is in a good place we're going to shift gears a little bit
and start working on our MCP client. The client can be found inside the MCP
client.py file inside the root project directory. Now before we do
anything inside this file I just want to give you a very quick reminder here.
Remember what I told you about earlier, usually in a typical project we are
either making use of a client or we are implementing a server. It's just in this
one particular project that we are working on that we are doing both, again
just so you can see both sides of the puzzle. Now the MCP client itself inside
of this file is consisting of a single class. You'll notice there's a lot of
code inside of here and it doesn't look quite as pretty as some of the code we
just wrote out inside of the server. So let me tell you exactly what's going on
inside this file and exactly why it is so large. Okay so inside this file we are
making the MCP client class. This class is going to wrap up something called a
client session. The client session is the actual connection to our MCP server.
This client session is a part of the MCP Python SDK. So again this session is
what gives us this connection to the outside server. The session itself
requires a little bit of resource cleanup. In other words whenever we close
down our program or decide that we don't need the server anymore we have to go
through a little bit of a cleanup process. And I have already written out a
lot of that cleanup code inside of the MCP client class. So that's really why
this class exists at all. Just to make that cleanup a little bit easier. You can
see some of that cleanup code inside of the connect function and down a little
bit lower at the cleanup async enter and async exit functions as well. So it's
very common practice to not just make use of this client session directly.
Instead very common to a wrap it up inside of a larger class that's going to
manage some of this different resource stuff for you. The next thing I want to
clarify is why this client exists at all. So in other words what is the client
really doing for us here. Well remember this flow that we looked at a little bit
ago. So we had our code right here and at certain points in time we needed say a
list of tools to send off to Claude. And then later on after that we also needed
to run a tool that was requested by Claude. In order to reach out to our MCP
server and get this list of tools or to run a tool that's where we are making
use of the MCP client. So we can imagine that this client is exposing some
functionality that belongs to the server to the rest of our code base. So inside
of our code base inside this project specifically inside of the core
directory there is a lot of code already inside there that I put together that is
making use of this class. So there are some other code that's going to call
some of the different functions you see inside of here like list tools, call tool,
list prompts, get prompt and so on. For right now in this video we're gonna
focus on implementing two functions list tools and call tool. So as you just saw
in the diagram we looked at a moment ago these two functions are going to be used
in different parts of our code base to get a list of tools to provide off to
Claude and eventually call a tool whenever Claude requests to call a tool.
Implementing these two functions is going to be really simple and
straightforward. So let me show you how we're going to do it. We'll first begin
with list tools. I'm going to remove the to do inside there and replace it with
result is await self dot session. I'm going to call that like a function list
underscore tools and then I will return result dot tools and that's it. So this
is going to get access to our session which is our actual connection to the
MCP server. It's going to call a built-in function to get a definition or
a list of all the different tools that are implemented by that server. I'm going
to get back result and then just return the tools and that's it. Then we can
implement call tool right here in a very similar fashion. So this will be
return await self dot session call tool tool name and tool input. Once again
getting access to the session that is our connection to the server and I'm
going to attempt to call a very specific tool. The name of the tool will be passed in
along with the input parameters or input arguments to it that were provided by
Claude. Now at this point in time I would like to test out these two functions
really quickly. To do so we're going to go down to the bottom of this file where
I put together a very small testing harness for us. So down here you'll
notice I put together this testing block so we can run this MCP client dot
py file directly and if we do so we're going to form a connection to our MCP
server and then we can just run some commands against it and just see what we
get back. Notice that in your version of the code there's a comment in there
about changing the command in args right here in case you are not making use of
UV. So if you're not using UV make sure you take a look at that comment. Inside
of this with block I'm going to add in a little bit of testing code so I'll say
result is await underscore client list tools and then I'm going to just print
out the result that we get back. So this should start up a copy of our MCP server
then attempt to get a list of all the different tools that are defined by it
and then just print out the result. To test this out I will flip back over to
my terminal and do a uv run MCP underscore client dot py and as usual if
you are not making use of UV you'll just do a Python MCP client dot py. Okay so
I'll run that and there is our list of tool definitions. So I can see inside of
here that I have the read doc contents tool which we put together a little bit
ago and our edit document tool as well. Each one has a description and a input
schema as well. So this is our tool definition which will eventually be
passed off to Claude. Now before we move on there's one other thing I want to
test. Remember we just implemented the function that's going to allow us to
list out some tools and pass them off to Claude and the function that's going to
allow us to call a tool that is implemented by the MCP server and then
pass the result off to Claude as well. I have already implemented the code that
is going to call list tools and call tool for us somewhere else inside this
project. So now that we have added in this functionality now that we have
defined these tools and the ability to call a particular tool we can now run
our CLI again and attempt to get Claude to make use of these tools. In other words
we can ask Claude to inspect the contents of some particular document and
even edit a document. So let me show you how we do that. Inside of my MCP server I
just want to give you a reminder that there is a document with a ID of
report.pdf and it has some text here of something like a 20 meter condenser
tower. I'm going to go back over to my terminal and I'm going to run my project
with a uvrun main.py and then I'm going to ask Claude what is the contents of
the report.pdf document and make sure you put in exactly report.pdf here.
And when we run this we're sending off along with the request our list of
tools. Claude is going to decide to use the read document tool and it's going to
get the contents of the document and then we will see that yes Claude was
able to get the contents of that document. We are told that the report is
something about a 20 meter condenser tower. Alright so at this point we have
added in some functionality around our client. Remember the client is what
allows us to access some functionality that is implemented inside of the MCP
server. At this point in time we have been able to list out some tools that
are created by the server and execute a tool that has been implemented by the
server.